Guide to the Sir William Jones Manuscripts, circa 1100-1794 MSS.301
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sir William Jones Manuscripts
circa 1100-1794
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jones, William, Sir, 1746-1794
MSS.301
2.5 Linear Feet in 3 small flat boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
William Jones (1746-1794) was a British lawyer in India and pioneer of comparative linguistic studies. Born in London in 1746, Jones later enrolled at University College, Oxford in 1764 and began studying linguistics and Oriental culture and literature. Jones studied Greek, Latin, Persian, Arabic and Sanskrit, becoming an expert in the field of comparative and historic linguistics. He spent several years after graduating working on translations of texts from these languages. After receiving his degree, he studied law at Middle Temple in London from 1770-1773. In 1772, William Jones became a fellow of the Royal Society as well as a practicing lawyer.
In 1783 he was knighted, becoming Sir William Jones, and was appointed to a position as a judge in British-controlled India. Jones continuted his studies of Oriental languages and literature in India, and during this time produced additional translations as well as original works. In addition to language and literature, Jones produced works on botony, astrology, zoology and law. In 1784 Sir William Jones founded the Asiatic Society with the purpose of promoting the study of Asiatic cultures and languages. Jones continued his studies and his work as a judge until his death in Calcutta in 1794.
Sources:
Cannon, Garland. The Collected Works of Sir William Jones, Vol., New York: NYU Press, 2003.
Jones, Sir William.The Poetical Works of Sir William Jones with the life of the author, Vol.1 London: Cadell and Davies, 1807.
Provenance
Fales purchased the materials from Jones scholar Garland Cannon with a generous donation from artist, writer and philanthropist Kevin Brine, an active supporter of the Elmer Holmes Bobst Library.
Scope and Contents
The Sir William Jones Manuscripts consist of various types of documents related to his lingustic studies, many in their original language with translations or notation by Jones. Included are documents in Sanskrit and Persian relating to astrology, botany and law.
Manuscripts, Bengali.; Marginalia (annotations); Manuscripts, Sanskrit.; Devanagari type.; zodiac.; Linguistics.; India -- History -- British occupation, 1765-1947.; Oriental philology.; Manuscripts, Persian.; Jones, William, Sir, 1746-1794
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Chart of Indian Zodiac signs (Raashi) in Devanagari characters, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Annotations in English & Persian. Original of the one printed later in Jones' "On the Antiquity of the Indian Zodiac." Annotation include seasons, planets & days of the week.
  - Legal Mutation, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Sanskrit written in Bengali characters. Refers to rules and regulations for donations/inheritance. Written in formal hand by a Brahmin scholar or pundit.
  - Sanskrit slokas (verses), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    written in Bengali characters. Formal writing. Handmade paper – rust/brown colored – writing in black ink.
  - Numbered sentences/slokas from 9-14, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Jones' handwriting with spelling corrections. Page number 3
  - Numbered sentences/slokas from 1-3, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Page number 1
  - Planet/zodiac related words, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Jones' handwriting
  - Short note, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters.
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Extract in Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Formal hand. English annotation by Jones. Mention of Jaitra Singh the ruler of Mewar (AD 1200)
  - Letter/short note to a senior person, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters.
  - Short note, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Handmade paper rust/brown colored – writing in black ink
  - 2 lines of slokas/note, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters
  - Slokas about the 'chatak' birds' love for the pure rain water and clouds, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Numbered slokas, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Last 2 lines are Sanskrit in Devanagari characters.
  - Numbered slokas, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. 4 page hand stitched notebook. First three pages are printed. The last page is Jones' handwriting – annotations for spellings and pronunciations of various Sanskrit words
  - Names of ancient Hindu texts and also newer (navin) ones, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated by Jones. Dated 20th July and 17th Aug 1788. Place – Benaras
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters, written in formal hand by a pundit.Handmade paper with writing in black ink and punctuation marks in red ink
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Formal writing by pundit – also Jones' handwriting. Back of page – English – reference to Varaha Mihira – an Indian astronomer, astrologer and mathematician. Also mention of Bhattotpala – the commentator of Brihat Jataka
  - Translation of Omar Khayyam's Rubaiyat (Quatrains), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Persian and English. Handwritten by Jones.
  - Plans of Knowledge, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    English. Jones' handwriting. 2 lines in Sanskrit. The cover reads "Paper of Literary Projects."
  - "Varahas Almanac", 1789 (Box 1, Folder 21a)
    - A calendar – 1789 – twelve months beginning from April. Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Also astrological study of lunar cycles
  - Preface to the Varahas Almanac for 1789 (Box 1, Folder 21b)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English - Jones' handwriting. Includes zodiac calculations
  - "A Hindu Almanac for the year of Saca – Beginning Sat 11th April 1789 by a Pandit of Navadwip, surnamed Vidya Siromani." (Box 1, Folder 21c)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. English annotations in Jones' handwriting. Mention of important festivals and auspicious occasions. Hand stitched notebook – handmade paper with silk cover
  - "A Hymn to the Night from the Veda.", undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Single sheet. English. Jones' handwriting
  - Manuscript on Ramadeva's poem Vivduanmodatarangini (Fountain of pleasure to the learned.), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Black in on brown paper. Inscription on cover is in English – "The Bidwan Mod Tarungeenee from the Gooptu Para Pundit of Santipore."
  - "Astronomical terms in Sanskrit used in Mr. Davis' paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English - Jones' handwriting
  - Translation of Necker used in 'On the mystical Poetry of the Persians and Hindus.', undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    English - Jones' handwriting.
  - "Account of the Method of Van Reede. Mr. W. Jones' Ms.", undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Opening translation from Reede tot Drakenstein's (1673) close to verbatim 'Botanical Observations on Select Indian Plants.'
  - Manuscript on Vetalapancavinsati by Sivadasa, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. 29 verses written in several hands – black ink. Hand painted notebook cover.
  - "Genera of plants growing between Arifnagar and Khidirpur.", 1794 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    English - Jones' handwriting. Incomplete, unpublished part of his catalog of Indian plants growing in Calcutta (1794).
  - "The Hindu Ecliptick.", undated (Box 1, Folder 29a)
    English. Diagram of globe with zodiac and seasons.
  - "The Yoga Stars.", undated (Box 1, Folder 29b)
    English. A chart with names of stars (nakshatras) along with the longitudes and latitudes.
  - "The Hindu Ecliptick.", undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Back of page – notes and calculations in Jones' handwriting.
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. 2 sentences in Persian
  - 'Yoga Vasistha.', undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English - Jones' handwriting. It is the discourse between Sage Vasistha and Lord Rama regarding truth and spiritual liberation.
  - Short Note, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Back of page reads "A Letter."
  - Floor plan, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Diagrams in red ink. Sanskrit in Devanagari characters – in black ink. Both sides of small note paper.
  - "Amara Cosha.", undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Title in English in Jones' handwriting. It is the oldest known dictionary in the world – classical Sanskrit vocabulary written by Sage Amara Sinha.
  - "Isavasyam" or And Upanishad from the Yajurveda, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    English translation of the Sanskrit text.
  - "Address to the Goddess Saraswati.", undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Title on cover page. English. 13 verses translated from Sanskrit. Jones' handwriting.
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Persian, 2 pages. I page Persian in English characters. Last page Persian in Jones' handwriting. Hand stitched notebook – writing in black ink.
  - "The Opening of the Shahnamah in the characters of the Zend.", undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Title in English. Rest of the manuscript in Persian. Shahnamah (The Book of Kings was written by Iranian poet Ferdowsi in 1000AD).
  - "On the Primitive Religion of the Hindus.", undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    English – Jones' handwriting.
  - Notes on the Gayatri Mantra, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Annotated by Jones. Writing in red ink, hand stitched 5 note books.
  - "Bengali Translation of the Dandakaumudi" (Punishment for Crime), undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Codes of judicial procedures.
  - Nala and Damayanti, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Hindu mythological narrative. Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated by Jones.
  - Letter from Garland Cannon, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    William Jones Accretions, 2003.
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Single document in Arabic/Persian. Single document in Arabic/Persian (?)
  - Legalities of Inheritance/Donation, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Single document in Bengali
  - Draft of Jones' translation of Gita Govinda – verses 4,5 & 6, c. 1790 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    (circa 1790). Originally composed by a Sanskrit poet Jayadeva. First English translation by Jones published in 1792. Othersie of page has Vedic slokas in Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in Jones'writing.
  - List of Sanskrit words and stanzas, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Annotations by Jones. Some words are names of deities and characters from the Ramayana and Mahabharata. General study of word meaning and spelling. Also includes a study of chhand (poetic meter). The Vedas contain Varnik and Matrik chhands.
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Two Persian words on cover - translated by Garland Cannon as BAZI SAT meaning "game" "chess". Material inside is foliated and perhaps does not relate/belong to the cover. Content inside written in Sanskrit in Bengali characters. Reference to Krishna and Arjun.
  - Formal declaration about various Shastras (disciplines of knowledge.), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Document in Sanskrit in Bengali characters.
  - Scansions of poetry using Indian musical notations/symbols, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    The other side of notebook has list of names in pencil – British officers and friends perhaps.
  - Translations of the Gayatri Mantra (prayer), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Sanskrit mantra written in English characters.
  - "Indian Grant of Law to the Priests of Siva.", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Devanagari and English characters. Last Page – "Reverence to Ganesha."
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Persian. Handmade paper with watermark.
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters
  - unidentified document, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Sanskrit in Bengali characters written by Nimai Pandit. Single sentence on the top is in Jones' handwriting.
  - "Translation of the poetry at Vindya Mountains.", undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated by Jones.
  - "Stanzas in praise of the Ganga.", undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Written in black ink. Persian words in red ink. Annotated in English by Jones. "King Akbar's minister Bairam Khan – a Muslim – but a poet in Sanskrit wrote several stanzas in praise of the Ganga." (river).
  - Extracts from the Vedas, Mahabharata and Shastras, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters. Annotated in English. Handmade paper, watermarked.
  - "The Ignorant Instructed.", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Sixteen stanzas of Moha Mudgara by Adi Sankaracharya. A short poem about the transitory nature of worldly experience – everlasting bliss can be gained through knowledge – the higher light. Original translations from Sanskrit to English.
  - Writings/Translations from the Yajurveda, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    English - Jones' handwriting. (Man as a tree).
  - Translations from the Vedas – "What Relish Can There Be…", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Extracts from the Vedas, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    commencing with "May that soul of mine…" English - Jones' handwriting
  - Jones' translations of extracts from the Vedas, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    English.
  - Chart of Hindi verbs, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Sanskrit in Devanagari characters with detailed explanations in English. Handmade paper. Writing in black ink.